Hi.
Oh, we've
never met each other in person. So, how
good
your name?
And I was just in a meeting with
I will follow up with her so we can
think about human response because if
you can I mean those are
the scopes and things. So, I'll follow
up with her.
was there and he was
waiting
to turn the sock.
I know. So, we just take a minute.
What are you doing?
Sorry, Ronald. Can we get this turned
around? So, you want it facing this way?
Yeah. I'm sorry. I like I said, I was
thinking about my cameras that face the
podium and
Yeah, we
don't know.
Is that it?
Good afternoon everyone.
Thank you all for being here.
I'm John Yuing, mayor of Omaha, and I
just want to express that we care deeply
for the families affected by the recent
ICE raids
and recognize the efforts of many
organizations that have activated a
rapid response team to provide legal
aid, humanitarian support, and help
reconnect children and youth with loved
ones.
Okay.
[Music]
There are many ways to show support.
First, check on neighbors and families
to see how they are doing. Second, there
are local organizations that help our
immigrant communities here in Omaha,
including by knowing what legal rights
someone has.
I've got
I've got someone on staff, Jennifer
Rodriguez, who is our community
relations and outreach coordinator, who
has been working very closely with
organizations and individuals to make
sure that people are receiving the
assistance they need.
Jennifer Rodriguez.
Third, we understand people want to show
public support through demonstrations.
If you choose to demonstrate, it is
important to be peaceful and understand
the city has requirements like permits
for public demonstrations.
We are aware of community-led effort
response teams doing legal and
humanitarian piece of support.
This has been ongoing for several months
now, working together that provide legal
assistance, basic needs, support, and
connecting those children and youth that
are left behind with the proper
relatives. So, I want to take a second
and just say thank you to all of the
folks that are working with our
immigrant population in these instances
because we know that children and
families are impacted in a tremendous
way when something like this happens.
Sorry, I kind of lost the last.
There has been some question about the
Omaha Police Department's role in this
incident yesterday. And with us we have
Chief Taj Moder to address that issue.
Would
it be easier? Are you going to translate
for me as well? Okay, no problem. Uh,
good afternoon everyone. My name is Todd
M, chief of police for the city of
Omaha. I want to go over the Omaha
Police Department's uh, knowledge of of
the event yesterday and when we became
involved, what our role was, and then
I'm going to take everybody through what
the two protest sites entailed. Uh first
of all, the Omal Police Department was
made aware in in an extremely general
basis that that ICE and Homeland
Security may be coming to Omaha. That
was about 10 days ago, right around that
time frame. Uh we didn't have any
specifics. We didn't really have
anything to pass on. It wasn't until the
morning of yesterday in which we were
contacted uh by the federal authorities
and they asked for traffic control and
we did provide traffic control just to
ensure a a safe environment. The Omaha
Police Department did not have any role
whatsoever in the uh detaining anybody
in the inception of this operation or
anything of that nature. We were
peripheral with traffic control only.
Once that was completed, we dig Segway
to monitor and ensure a peaceful protest
and ensure First Amendment rights at two
protest sites. The first one was at 32nd
and L Street, 33rd and L Street, right
around that area. At its peak, there
were 400 participants in this in this
protest. Uh there was no arrest made and
there was one assault report was taken
um on behalf of a protester.
The second protest site was at 72nd and
Dodge. And at its peak at 72nd and
Dodge, there was 200 protesters. That
protest venue, there was no issues, no
violations, very minimal police
involvement there at all other than just
monitoring.
And then of course as the law
enforcement agency for Omaha, we
continue to monitor any promptu protest,
anything that may come up on the fly and
also this weekend as it may pertain to
the College World Series or any protest
of that of that like. So the
demonstrations protest the the role of
the police department will be to ensure
a safe environment to enforce the laws.
We try to get with everybody before to
lay out what the laws are so that we do
have that peaceful protest. But our
primary objective is to ensure first
amendment rights, plain and simple. So
we do encourage uh protest
demonstrations. We just ask that it be
done peacefully. Work with the Omaha
Police Department in advance and it's
the best way that we can ensure that. So
I'm going to be available here for
questions along with the mayor, I
presume. And at at this point in time,
I'm going to uh step aside.
The mayor's office. The mayor's office
has also been involved with our partners
from the county board as well as the
city council and monitoring the
circumstances with them as well. So, we
have with us today president of the
county board, Mr. Roger Garcia, and also
city council president Danny Begley.
Good afternoon. going to speak a little
bit about the impacts of these
activities yesterday in Omaha. So, we
know that for those of us who live here,
as we drive across the city on any
normal day, we see our thriving,
contributing immigrant community across
the many sectors and vocations that they
contribute to. here in Omaha. We can
drive down any road and if there's a
construction site, many times there's
immigrant individuals there working the
site helping build our infrastructure.
Here in Omaha, we go to a restaurant.
Many times there might be an immigrant
population uh helping us serve some
delicious food and cook up some
delicious food. We have immigrant
community involved in education in all
of our business sectors across the
community contributing to what we eat on
our plate every meal as well in the
agriculture sector across Nebraska which
is um very much immigrantheavy and
contributes to our nutrition every day.
So we see the contributions
and we also see the impact that can
happen when even
one person from a family member is all
of a sudden
disappears
you know for that family and you know
mom is gone, dad is gone, uh a child is
gone. When we hear a story, a news line
of one family member going away all of a
sudden, that alone is very traumatizing
to a community.
Now, we can envision
approximately
80 family members in one day all of a
sudden to that family disappearing. We
don't know where they went. We don't
know where they're going. and we don't
know what the future holds for them. So,
I speak from the perspective of the
immigrant community, the Latino
community, and those who care about the
individuals affected and impacted
yesterday. There are still a lot of
unanswered questions, which we welcome
clarification for. We welcome more
information in regards to who has been
detained, uh a list of names, where
they're being held, where they're going
to be detained, and uh any other details
that would be helpful. As there are, of
course, as mentioned, many individuals
in the community that want to help, want
to contribute resources to the impacted
families, make sure they have legal
representation,
uh and so forth. So, we do give our
thanks to everybody who stepped up
yesterday. There was a great deal of
organizations and individuals who spent
all day trying to sort through uh what
really was a chaotic tornado of
information because we didn't know what
was true and what was not. We spent all
day trying to verify stories of are they
actually at this location or are they
not at this location. And so we welcome
more information uh now and uh in any
other circumstance we may need it. Of
course, we wish as an impacted community
that uh these large largecale operations
uh do not continue to happen as we
understand
of course being a supporter of law
enforcement and of community safety. If
there are individuals here or in any
other city that is truly involved in
high level criminal activity,
um you know the obvious ones of uh
physical assault, sexual assault,
murders,
criminal activity, cartel activity, any
serious crime, of course we understand
those individuals will meet uh their
repercussions from a law perspective and
law enforcement perspective. We
understand that. But
the individuals caught up yesterday,
at least from the personal stories that
I am aware of,
did not fit that profile.
I have um a loving wife who many of you
know in this audience. Her aunt, her
mother's sister, has been detained.
She's lived here for decades. She's
raised a family here.
She's contributed back to the Omaha
community and the economy. We from our
perspective, we can assure you she was
not involved in any high level criminal
activity.
I have college friends who have had
their mothers detained as well. So, I am
just telling a very honest narrative
of how this impacts our community. We
want to work well with all levels of law
enforcement from local to federal to
truly tackle any high level crimes and
address uh those concerns and keep our
community safe always while also having
a heart for individuals who are here
raising families, contributing to our
economy and our society and might be in
an undocumented status but that's it.
there in that status, but also at the
same time members of our community who
have in many cases been here for decades
who have many cases never had any kind
of criminal activity in their profile at
all. And so those are the things that uh
we have some concerns about. Those are
some things that um big picture the
reverberations
that have come across the community to
instill continued fear and anxiety as we
don't know if these kind of activities
will continue today across the week. And
so there's a lot of unanswered
questions, a lot of continued fears. Our
thriving 24th Street business community
shut down yesterday in the afternoon.
Some of those business owners have
decided to not open their doors today.
So, we just want to have that sense of
peace. We are called to be peacemakers
and not agents of the contrary. So, uh
we want to all partner to bring restore
that peace and vibrancy that we know
Omaha is. Thank you.
Thank you, Commissioner. Now we have
city council president Danny Begley.
Good afternoon everyone. it. The last
couple days have kind of shaken
everybody here in our community. And as
the new council president, I've worked
with Mayor Euing here who's hit the
ground running with great connection and
knowledge of trying to help people the
best we can. I've gotten contacts in my
office. I appreciate Commissioner
Garcia, the great work he does for our
community and the impacts that this is
having. I don't have family members like
Commissioner Garcia that are impacted,
but like many of you, I have family and
friends that are teachers in our local
school systems, and we know the impacts
of the families that are taking place
here with the raids in the last couple
days. We can't do this enough to provide
the information for people. I've been
trying to share it on my social media
and anybody that contacts my office.
The Center for Immigration Refugee
Advancement, many of us have heard about
that the last day or two. Many of us
have known about it for a long time.
That number is 402884876.
How can we help the people that are
impacted? That's one. The second one is
donations to the Heartend Workers
Center. You can contact 4029336095
and they're located down at 4923 South
24th Street in Old South Omaha.
Also, another resource is the Nebraska
Immigration Legal Services Hotline.
They're located at 4223 Center Street.
They have proono services. They're
available for those that are impacted.
That number is a toll-free number of
6730.
I'll continue to do all I can to help
people in the community that have been
imp that have been impacted by this and
their lives set upside down. But I want
to thank again Mayor Ewing for the good
communication we've had. And I want to
partner with him and everybody here
today to make the dignity of the
families that have been impacted by this
to try to make it as helpful as we can
for our community because that's what
they need the most here today and every
day. Thank you, mayor. Thank you.
Next, we have the city's human rights
and relations director, Kayn Deleus.
Hi everyone. I'm the director of the
human rights and relations department.
The department is responsible for
investigating allegations of
discrimination in employment, housing,
and public accommodations. We do
economic develop economic development.
We have a restorative justice program
that we partner to facilitate. We do a
lot of outreach and education. And we're
working on the poverty elimination
action plan for Omaha right now.
I'm gonna speak in Spanish as well.
economic
restor.
I don't support a culture of fear.
I am very impressed by our community
coming together to provide so many
resources and being prepared to support
one another.
I want to share a few of the resources
today.
Three of our consulates are here right
now. The Mexican consulate who you can
reach in an emergency at 402
3125006
or their general number is 4025951841.
numeroco
the consulate of El Salvador. You can
reach at 4025021030.
Cinco
and the consulate of Guatemala. You can
reach at 531
0236.
You can and in an emergency 531-9990083.
Ceros.
There are two other resources which
council president Begley mentioned and
I'll mention them in Spanish.
Heartland Workers Center.
The Heartland Worker Center has
information for know your rights, family
safety planning, and for business owners
and more. The Center for Immigrant and
Refugee Advancement.
Uh my office is always here to
communicate information to the public,
to share resources, and to hear back
from people. So please be in touch if
you if you need information or have
information. We're always here for that.
Gracias.
Thank you. And I will offer a brief
summary and then we'll take any
questions that you all may have.
Oh,
Jennifer. Okay. I'm sorry. We also have
our South Omaha community liaison,
Jennifer Rodriguez. Sorry. Um, but just
briefly just wanted to highlight the
community work that we're doing
together. Also wanted to highlight the
together. the organizations are coming
um together like Harland Worker Center,
Sira as well, the consulate Mexico,
Guatemala, Salador and so we open our
doors and we welcome all the community
organizations as well that want to help
our community. Um and also um just like
our mayor um mentioned, I am the
community relations and outreach
coordinator. So also um able to
hear for any questions in support of the
community.
Work
center.
Okay, thank you. Now I will offer just a
brief summary of yesterday. We received
word of the raid and then we began with
Jennifer Kalin, Chief Smer, my chief of
staff, Tom Warren, our
assistant chief deputy for
communications,
Aaron Grace, try to find out what the
facts were. One of the things we don't
believe is appropriate is for us to make
comments without knowing the facts
because then we become part of the
problem and part of the hysteria. So we
wanted to find answers. We found those
answers. We were going to do a press
conference yesterday afternoon. We were
told that there was going to be a
demonstration. And so we knew if we did
a press conference then I'd probably be
talking to an empty room. So we didn't
do that because we wanted to give this
issue the attention that it deserves.
That's why we set a time for a press
conference so that we could share what
we knew and what we did and our partners
as well that have done a great job of
assisting families because at the end of
the day this truly impacts children and
families. And if you know anything about
my background from the Omaha Police
Department, you know that I care about
children and families. So, we wanted to
get the services in place. We wanted to
get people the help they needed and we
wanted to provide an accurate story. So
what we've done today is provided the
information that we knew and shared that
with you. Certainly this does impact our
community and it does create fear. We
understand when we go and we arrest
people that are violent offenders,
people who have committed serious
crimes, and I'm all for that as mayor of
this city and a public servant for 43
and a half years. But we want to ensure
that people are treated fairly and that
they have due process in the course of
these things. So with that, we will
answer any questions that you might
have. Yes. In regards to the raids
yesterday, you tell me about what time
you guys found out about it versus what
time it actually happened. And then also
I also have a question for sure. And he
would be better to answer that question
about when we found out as well.
I can repeat.
Can you tell me what time you found out
about the rates yesterday versus when
uh question was what time did we find
out about the rays versus when they
happened? We we got called uh for
traffic control pretty much as they were
staging. So, it's pretty pretty close in
time proximity. We weren't involved in
any of the pre-planning or the
pre-staging or anything of that nature.
We found out uh right before we received
uh word that they needed traffic control
and and we responded at that point. That
that's essentially it. You also said
about 10 days ago
that government address some is coming.
Yep. Um can you tell me where you got
that information? I I really I can't.
Yeah, it's it's going to be classified
and we're not we're not in we're not in
the business of committing any crimes. I
can't divulge certain things from a law
enforcement perspective. What I can tell
you though is it was so general in
nature and even the even the time and
the date and there was it was that
nebulous. Okay. So, we just received
general awareness. Did not know what was
coming, what day, what time or anything
of that nature and definitely not a
location.
Um, I'm not sure on the exact detainment
numbers. The last I heard it was over 70
were detained. As far as the location
where that detainment is, I'm not at
liberty to say.
I have no idea because here's here's why
I don't know. Because we want we're not
a part of this operation.
Our our role from the Omal Police
Department was simply traffic control
and to ensure the protests were as
peaceful as possible. We did not
intervene involved in the raid
enforcement piece at all. nor do we have
an operational role in in processing any
detainees and nor do they inform us of
that
the the Omaha Police Department it's
it's really out of our hands at this
point once they enter into the
detainment of ICE or Homeland Security
I would ask you
The question was, do we have any
indication of any future raids? And
we've heard a lot of talk, but we don't
have anything specific that tells us
that this is going to happen again. So,
we're hoping that it doesn't obviously
because of the chaos it creates in the
community, but we don't have any
specific information.
coordinated effort. You know that other
organizations?
So the coordinating uh give me a second
here and I'll pull it up. The question
of me was what agencies were involved in
this and what agencies coordinated and
actually facilitated in the the raid per
se. Yeah. Okay.
So obviously was US Customs,
US Immigration and Customs Enforcement,
ICE, Homeland Security had a role,
the Department of Justice, the FBI, the
Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, and
Firearms,
the DEA, Drug Enforcement
Administration, United States Marshall
Service, uh, Internal Revenue Service
had a role, and the US Citizenship and
Immigration Services.
And those would be your federal agencies
that were involved. And locally,
locally, you had the Omaha Police
Department doing traffic control. Um,
the State Patrol had a role. I'm not
100% sure what theirs was. Douglas
County Sheriff's Department assisted us
with traffic.
Did you have a question?
When you say you're not
It means I can't say
I have no idea.
No, I cannot. I mean I I I as a law
enforcement officer there are there is
certain information that I can't divulge
otherwise I I enter into committing a
crime and I just can't. And the families
Yeah, I don't know. The question was,
have the families been informed as to
where their loved ones are at? Um, you
know, I don't know. Those would be
questions posed for some of the federal
agencies that I just listed. I I
absolutely don't know that answer.
Yes.
I'd like to know if
the administration support.
Sure. The question was, do I support
these workplace raids and do I have any
influence? The answer to both questions
unfortunately
on the second one, but the first
question is I answer is I certainly do
not support them. The second question I
don't have any influence on how this is
done. Do you know why
at this point in time and uh what can
you tell me about what you know about
that person? Sure. I don't know why. I
can speculate which I don't do and so I
can only tell you publicly that I don't
know why Omaha was targeted
and I believe you were trying to answer
this but does it bother you that this
happened and for you what's your message
to the public? Absolutely. Well my first
message to the public is to know that we
are with them. We will work with the
agencies that are doing great work for
those citizens or those uh members of
our community. We have our staff working
on this, partnering with people and
getting people informed as well. So, we
will continue to do that, do everything
we can to support them.
Question.
I think you have a question.
I think the question
yesterday.
So, let me paraphrase your question.
Yeah, it's a long question.
If the Omal Police Department is not
involved in any aspect of this, why were
there uniform patrol officers at the
scene? Why would they aid ICE? And why
would they aid ICE? Um, my my answer to
that is is we we weren't part of the
aiding
uh function of this. We were peripheral
to ensure traffic enforcement, to assure
public safety as it traversed up and
down that line. As far as the planning,
as far as the raid, as far as knowledge
of the operation, anything of that
nature, as far as entering into the
building, Omaha Police Department did
not have a role in that. Now, it is on a
public streets nearby. And so, it would
be prudent to have law enforcement there
just to ensure that aspect is peaceful.
And then of course we did transfer into
monitoring the protest sites to ensure
uh first amendment liberties were intact
first and foremost and then just to make
sure things stayed peaceful there. That
was that was our our role in this. It
did not extend any further than that and
it won't in the future as well.
Sure. The the follow-up question was,
can I speak to the appearance that we
were there and the appearance that we we
may have been involved? And that
appearance, I'm going to presume, I'm
going to add this, can cause someone in
our our community to wonder, is the Omal
Police Department someone to be fearful
of. Will we be checking for immigration
papers? Will we be checking people's
status? I I can ensure the public that
the Omal Police Department will not be
involved in checking immigration status,
legal status in our community. That is
not our mission. Our mission is uh
public safety. Our mission is police
community relations. Our mission is that
for this reasons, I need victims to come
forward. They will not come forward if
they're fearful of Omal Police
Department being immigration officers.
I need witnesses to come forward. I
don't want an underlying bed of of
crimes that are occurring that we're not
aware of and that victim can't get any
help because immigration status. That's
why I want to make it very clear to our
community that's deeply affected by what
took place yesterday.
At any time you can reach out to the
Omal Police Department, 911, flag us
down, call us, go to one of our
stations, and you will never be we will
never alter what we do to check your
legal status. It is only after an arrest
is made for significant crime, serious
crime. At that point in time,
immigration status would be checked, but
not by the police department. That's
that's about the crisp as I can say it.
And I think I was very clear in the
press release yesterday as well that the
Omaha Police Department is not going to
be engaged in immigration enforcement.
That is a continuation of a practice and
policy under the previous mayor and I
supported that during the campaign and I
support that now. That will always be
our stance for this community as long as
I'm mayor of Omaha, Nebraska.
Mayor,
Mr. Mayor and Chief, I am very
impressed.
The people you have assembled here,
Mr. Mayor, we're going to leave. We're
going to go to DC LA. We're going to go
back to DC. What do you want us to carry
as your message to the members of
Congress? Sure.
What do you tell Congress that you want?
The thing I would want you to tell
Congress is let's develop a
comprehensive
immigration policy that actually works.
Right now, what is happening across this
country is a lot of fear is being
created. We don't have a comprehensive
or even understandable
approach to immigration, especially when
it comes to our Latino members of this
country. And so I would want them to
come up with a comprehensive
immigration plan that they've been
talking about for decades
and do something that helps hardworking
people in these communities be able to
have an opportunity to become citizens
of this country because they are
contributing
to our cities. They are contributing to
our states and they are contributing to
our nation. So let's do this in a way
that makes sense. That's not soft on
crime or anything. It's humanitarian.
These are people. These are not
statistics. So let's take care of the
people in our cities, in our state, and
in our country.
Excellent.
Sorry. Mayor Y. Um, could you explain
your concerns about volatility of the
current political climate?
Yes. What I what I see is a lot of
uncertainty
and I see a lot of chaos and I see a lot
of fear where people shut down
businesses yesterday,
people shut down a community college
yesterday, people shut down a library
yesterday. Those things create
uncertainty and fear and keep our city
from being as productive and as
welcoming as I would like us to be. Have
you spoken to mayors with other cities
who are currently?
I have not spoken to them. I've reached
out to some of them and then some of
them have reached out to me. I've been
doing mayor stuff today so I have not
been able to have those conversations.
But yes, we will have those
conversations as well.
Yes, sir.
the city.
Our police department is always
preparing and they're always looking at
what the possibilities are, what the
contingencies are, and I believe they've
got a great plan to help make sure any
protests or demonstrations that we have
will be peaceful. and we will do
whatever we can to make sure we're also
being good host for the people traveling
from other parts of the country to our
great city.
Yes. Without visiting released a
statement yesterday saying they intended
on speaking with you
a couple other people too. Has that
happened yet? And do you plan? If they
have time I am going to meet with them
after this meeting because
Okay. Because I literally had two press
conferences before this today and then
we have other budget meetings and things
that we have to do as well, but we would
be glad to meet with them.
Yes.
you're you're always worried about trust
when you're in law enforcement because
it's a very fragile thing. And so you
have to continue to do the work every
day. That's what I did for my 24 years
and nine months with the police
department was work on that every day.
And I know Chief's Moder does that as
well.
So I I will add to that. Obviously trust
with our community is is really
paramount. It's how we we keep crime
low. It's how we keep people safe. It it
adds a good element to our city when the
police and the community work together.
I would ask for some assistance on that
front from from everybody in the room,
from the media, everybody in this room.
So many things are thrown out there when
something large happens as did yesterday
in our community. So many rumors, so
many things get out there.
There has to be credible messengers.
There has to be information taken back
to disseminate what is actually
occurring and what is not occurring. And
that's the one of the primary reasons
the mayor held this press conference
today to really delineate what took
place and and then the rest we can just
say, okay, that did not happen. That was
a rumor. And so I would ask that that we
all take this time as partners in this.
Let's let's get the record straight as
to what took place yesterday. And as we
move forward, they're going to continue
to be rumors and and we get that. We
totally understand that the Omal Police
Department has an intelligence unit. We
we're constantly monitoring what's going
on. We try to get in front of it and
dispel rumors. It wasn't but 10 minutes
ago that we put out on our social media
dispelling the rumor that our Latino
Peace Officers Association had had
information on uh future uh raids or
anything like that. They don't. That
bulletin was was not accurate. It was
fake and they just they labeled it as
our Latino Peace Officers Association.
So, it's those types of things that we
need help with. When that occurs, we're
going to put it out as as fast as
possible and we need immediately to
repeat it as well when that comes up.
Yes. News stations
last night
and there were emergency medical
services people there
involved.
I have not received any information to
indicate they were, but I just don't
know.
I'm not I'm not sure if they actually
came to the scene, but I I did hear of
of a potential exposure incident that
occurred inside. If that was the case,
the Omaha Fire Department would come and
provide treatment. And by by all means,
if somebody's hurt inside that building
during the course of this raid or any
other time, the fire department's going
to come and they're going to render aid.
When you come into this city, as far as
I'm concerned, as far as Chief Bossman,
who's the fire chief, is concerned, when
you're in our city, we we don't care
what your status is, what's going on.
You you you deserve the protection of
the police department. You deserve the
Omaha Fire Department fire and rescue to
come to your aid if you need something.
That's the way we view it.
um
I'm curious how philosophical handl
I have not talked to governor pill and I
have not seen a statement so I can't
speculate on what he said what I will
always try to do is work with the
governor and other leaders in this
community just as we have with um
members of the city council and the
county board
But we are going to look at what we
believe is best for the people of Omaha.
Thank you everybody.
Thanks for coming.
Thank you.
Thanks.